“Follow the stars.”
I heard the voice of Nunyati in my head.
“They will guide you. They have guided migrants for generations.
Otherwise, don’t trust anyone. Just yourself. You are on your own now, Mawusi. We willow warblers are solo travellers. That’s the only way to be safe.”
Back then, I remember listening to him in total disbelief. How could I ever know my way in total darkness, without a map, without someone to show me the way?
I envied the sparrows, the geese, who travelled in flocks, following the older, more experienced migrants. I was alone.
And yet, he was right. I realised I knew the way. Without a doubt, I trusted my ancestors’ heritage, and I flew, as fast as the wind.
How could I ever describe that feeling? That sense of total freedom? That sensation that you are finally meeting your destiny? It was exhilarating. I felt invincible.
I was racing into the night, further and faster than I had ever gone. Me who had never flown more than a few miles!
I saw the men’s lights beneath me, those little electric lines of roads and villages, like a spiderweb. They looked so small, so frail. You can’t catch me now, I laughed.
And then, suddenly, the spiderweb stopped. There was just total darkness. A world of shadows.
My heart started racing, so I decided to land on a tree at the limit of the men’s kingdom to rest. The sun was rising at the horizon. And then, I saw it.
Ahead of me lay an area of unimaginable emptiness. An immense stretch of land that humans had been too terrified to conquer.
And here I was, a little bird, knowing that my destiny was beneath it.
The world’s greatest desert. The Sahara.